Guide to the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina Records, 1960-2020; 1960-ongoing and undated RL.00012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Legal Program Series, 1968-2006 and undated, 260 boxes
  - Case Files Subseries, 128 boxes
    - 1980s Case Files
      - Middle school suspensions for Confederate flag T-shirts (Box 187)
      - Motorist's prayer on state distributed maps (Box 187)
      - Sexual harassment (Box 187)
      - Unlawful incarceration (Box 187)
      - Improper sanctions, 2 folders (Box 187)
      - Misuse of hypnosis in court (Box 187)
      - Discrimination on the basis of HIV status, Louisiana (Box 187)
      - Incarceration without appointed style (Box 187)
      - Attorney's fees (Box 187)
      - Mental illness applied to a minor (Box 187)
      - At-large election systems, discrimination (Box 188)
      - Jurors precluded from considerations of mitigating evidence (Box 188)
      - Question of governmental immunity (Box 188)
      - Eighth Amendment (Box 188)
      - Judge opens court with a prayer (Box 188)
      - Use of community standards in obscenity trials (Box 188)
      - Cross burnings (Box 188)
      - Prior restraint, issue of nudity in a musical (Box 188)
      - Prison libraries (Box 188)
      - Prisoner deprived of right to effective counsel (Box 188)
      - NC obscenity statute (Box 188)
      - Blood tests (Box 188)
      - Racial discrimination in jury selection (Box 188)
      - Sodomy laws (Box 188)
      - Indigent defense (Box 188)
      - Prenatal conduct used as basis for indictment of assault (Box 188)
      - Scriptural authority invoked in the application of the death penalty (Box 188)
      - Community standard in obscenity trial (Box 188)
      - Obscenity trial (Box 188)
      - Obscenity trial (Box 188)
      - Strip search (Box 188)
      - Belhaven County permit ordinance (Box 188)
      - Police officer terminated for speaking at city council meeting (Box 188)
      - Prison sentence for writing threatening letters to the president, ineffective counsel (Box 188)
      - Polygraph control questions (Box 188)
      - 2 Live Crew: obscenity trial, Florida (Box 189)
      - Murder, mistrial (Box 189)
      - Due process (Box 189)
      - Civil forfeiture (Box 189)
      - At-large election systems, discriminatory (Box 189)
      - Abortion rights (Box 189)
      - Red squad files kept on student activist (Box 189)
      - Medical care in prison (Box 189)
      - Closing of homeless shelter due to city zoning ordinance (Box 189)
      - Prisoner's Rights Project Referrals (Box 189)
      - Fired for Ku Klux Klan membership (Box 189)
      - Standardized tests (Box 189)
      - Concerned Citizens: Hendersonville parade permits (Box 189)
      - Denial of pool hall license (Box 189)
      - Road race at a Christian school (Box 189)
      - Charlotte: playboy sold at airport (Box 189)
      - Robeson County: Demons (Box 189)
      - KAIA, Inc.: bingo license (Box 189)
      - Deliberate indifference, Mitchell County jail (Box 189)
      - Air Traffic Controllers: urine testing (Box 189)
      - CP and L Nuclear Power Plant: drug testing (Box 189)
      - Johnston County: challenge to at-large election system (Box 189)
      - Murder trial appeal, right to testify in one's own defense, 1-11 of 19 folders (Box 190)
      - Murder trial appeal, right to testify in one's own defense, 12-19 of 19 folders (Box 191)
      - Hatch Act firing (Box 192)
      - Request for assistance on appeal, denied (Box 192)
      - Prisoner denied access to Hustler magazine (Box 192)
      - Inadequate medical care in prison (Box 192)
      - Unlawful search and seizure (Box 192)
      - Charges of racial discrimination (Box 192)
      - Robeson County Clerk: sharing information over the phone (Box 192)
      - Fayetteville: voting rights (Box 192)
      - Chronic insomnia (Box 192)
      - Greenfield Inn: racial discrimination (Box 192)
      - Bertie County: voting rights (Box 192)
      - Prisoner with Vitiligo forced to work outside (Box 192)
      - Festival in the Park, Charlotte: non-profit participation (Box 192)
      - Due process (Box 192)
      - Reidsville: city council, voting re-districting (Box 192)
      - Rejects: closed 1989 Jan. 11 (Box 192)
      - Odom Correctional Unit, conditions (Box 192)
      - Prisoner rights (Box 192)
      - Greensboro: press credentials, coverage of Ku Klux Klan rally (Box 192)
      - Death-row inmate stabbed, charge of neglect (Box 192)
      - Racial exclusion in juries (Box 192)
      - Prisoner's rights (Box 192)
      - Police misconduct (Box 192)
      - Prisoner, medical malpractice (Box 192)
      - Racial Classification (Box 192)
      - Waynesville sign ordinance (Box 192)
      - NCD.O.T. eye testing policy (Box 192)
      - Nutrition, First Amendment legislation (Box 192)
      - Ineffective assistance of counsel (Box 192)
      - Raleigh: gay discrimination (Box 192)
      - Fourth Amendment (Box 192)
      - Improper investigation of her son's death, ruled a suicide (Box 192)
      - Adoption (Box 192)
      - Auto-theft (Box 192)
      - Guilford Alliance for Gay and Lesbian Equality (Box 192)
      - Raleigh City Council: zoning ordinances (Box 192)
      - False arrest (Box 192)
      - Rejections, 1989, Apr. - July (Box 193)
      - Handicap (Box 193)
      - School beatings (Box 193)
      - Misc. Correspondence (Box 193)
      - Rejections Misc. (Box 193)
      - Terminated from employment for affair with a fellow employee, pregnancy (Box 193)
      - License revoked (Box 193)
      - Immigration (Box 193)
      - Police misconduct (Box 193)
      - Right to counsel (Box 193)
      - Questions about a capital trial (Box 193)
      - Treatment of service maladies (Box 193)
      - Racial discrimination (Box 193)
      - Domestic rights (Box 193)
      - Religious clothing in prison (Box 193)
      - Student stripped searched (Box 193)
      - Fourth Amendment, bus stops (Box 193)
      - Ku Klux Klan, Durham (Box 193)
      - Revoked building permit (Box 193)
      - AIDS issue (Box 193)
      - Speedy trial right (Box 193)
      - DA used criminal courts for civil issue (Box 193)
      - Public drunk and disorderly (Box 193a)
      - AIDS discrimination (Box 193a)
      - Federal government employee questionnaire (Box 193a)
      - Northampton County personnel ordinance (Box 193a)
      - Town clerk (Box 193a)
      - CIA protesters, UNC-CH (Box 193a)
      - Daughter harassed by teacher (Box 193a)
      - AIDS in prison (Box 193a)
      - Hiring of underage caregiver (Box 193a)
      - Use of force in school (Box 193a)
      - Down's Syndrome (Box 193a)
      - Child support case (Box 193a)
      - Prejudiced judge (Box 193a)
      - East Carolina University racial incident (Box 193a)
      - Sentencing involved discrimination over HIV status (Box 193a)
      - Insurance cancellation (Box 193a)
      - Held in jail without probable cause (Box 193a)
      - Sexual discrimination (Box 193a)
    - 1990s Cases Files
      - Racial profiling, 1990, 6 folders (Box 193a)
      - Due process, 1990, folders 1-8 of 11 (Box 194)
      - Due process, 1990, folders 9-11 of 11 (Box 195)
      - Unaffiliated candidate wants name to be on Durham County ballot, 1990, 3 folders (Box 195)
      - Sons of Confederate Veterans, denied access to city festival, 1992, 4 folders (Box 195)
      - Singer Entertainment, Oh! Calcutta, denied performance space due to nudity, 1991, 1-3 of 9 folders (Box 195)
      - Singer Entertainment, Oh! Calcutta, denied performance space due to nudity, 1991, 4-9 of 9 folders (Box 196)
      - Students for the Ethical Treatment of Animals (SETA) v. UNC: denied access to document relating to care of lab animals, 1989 (Box 196)
      - Southern Appalachian Lesbian and Gay Alliance (SALGA): refusal by DOT to allow SALGA to participate in adopt-a-highway, 1990, 1-3 of 7 folders (Box 196)
      - Refusal by DOT to allow SALGA to participate in adopt-a-highway, 1990, 4-7 of 7 folders (Box 197)
      - Dismissed for questioning publicly credentials of emergency services coordinator, 1990, 8 folders (Box 197)
      - Accused rapist denied racial balance on grand jury, 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 197)
      - Prisoners' rights, 1990 (Box 197)
      - Confidentiality of attorney / inmate correspondence, 1989 (Box 197)
      - Police officer fired for speaking at a town council meeting against a proposed schedule/pay change, 1989, 3 folders (Box 198)
      - Dismissed for refusing to take polygraph test, 1989, 5 folders (Box 198)
      - Lesbian denied being foster parent, 1991 (Box 199)
      - Challenge to state law exempting bibles from sales tax, 7 folders (Box 199)
      - Criminal prosecution of drug use during pregnancy, 1-3 of 13 folders (Box 199)
      - Criminal prosecution of drug use during pregnancy, 4-13 of 13 folders (Box 200)
      - Use of hypnosis in court testimony, 1-2 of 3 folders (Box 200)
      - Use of hypnosis in court testimony, 3 of 3 folders (Box 201)
      - Ku Klux Klan:
        - Apex (Box 201)
        - Kings Mtn. (Box 201)
        - Roxboro (Box 201)
        - Ayden (Box 201)
        - Varina (Box 201)
        - Wilmington (Box 201)
      - Prisoners' rights, equal protection (Box 201)
      - Farmworkers legal service of NC: migrant farmer's rights (Box 201)
      - Corporal punishment, day care, 6 folders (Box 201)
      - Destruction of The Appalachian Collection, 9 folders (Box 202)
      - Solicitation on Forsyth County Technical College Campus (Box 202)
      - Bible tax exemption (Box 202)
      - Junior high school students suspended for wearing t-shirts with confederate flags, 1-2 of 9 folders (Box 202)
      - Junior high school students suspended for wearing t-shirts with confederate flags, 3-9 of 9 folders (Box 203)
      - Sustainer Program (Box 203)
      - Morristown Library policy, 2 folders (Box 203)
      - Complaint against a judge who opens court with a prayer, 1990-1992, 1-5 of 11 folders (Box 203)
      - Complaint against a judge who opens court wtih a prayer, 1990-1992, 6-11 of 11 folders (Box 204)
      - Oaths, religious freedom (Box 204)
      - Turkey parade (Box 204)
      - Tom Vass candidate for senate, 1992 (Box 204)
      - Protesting turkey olympics, 1992 (Box 204)
      - Class at UNC-CH, speaking to a legal writing class 1992 (Box 204)
      - Class, speaking to a legal writing class, 1991 (Box 204)
      - Girl wants to attend school outside her district, 1992 (Box 204)
      - Rock the Vote, denied access to voter registration lists, 1992 (Box 204)
      - Columbia High School (Box 204)
      - Voting system discrimination, 1992, 2 folders (Box 205)
      - Nude performance art in Asheville (Box 205)
      - Durham County School Board elections, voting rights issue (Box 205)
      - Metrolina Community Service Board Casino Night: gay rights (Box 205)
      - Student Environment Action Coalition: UNC solicitation policy (Box 205)
      - Man beaten by state trooper (Box 205)
      - Religious freedom for prisoners, 1993 (Box 205)
      - AIDS testing (Box 205)
      - Death penalty overturned, 1989 (Box 205)
      - Religious headwear, 1993 (Box 205)
      - Onslow Co: Gay harassment (Box 205)
      - Establishment clause, 1987 (Box 205)
      - Day care and no lobby rules (Box 205)
      - Craven County Community College: school graduation prayers, 1991 (Box 205)
      - Prior restraint, 1991 (Box 205)
      - Death penalty, court of military appeals, 1991 (Box 205)
      - Peace tax fund (Box 205)
      - Strategic Lawsuit Against Public Participation (SLAPP suit) 1992 (Box 205)
      - Chapel Hill: gay/lesbian rights, 1992 (Box 205)
      - Tarheel Jr. Historian: article written by ACLU lawyer, William Simpson (Box 205)
      - Civil commitment: guilty but insane (Box 205)
      - Asheville, picketing ordinance, 1991 (Box 206)
      - Athletes in Action: religious organization utilizing UNC Stadium, 1990 (Box 206)
      - Carolina Gay and Lesbian Association, 1992 (Box 206)
      - Durham Chapters, Hard Choices (Box 206)
      - Bibles distributed at schools, 1990 (Box 206)
      - Collection of race information, 1991 (Box 206)
      - Racial classification (Box 206)
      - Racial classification, 1990 (Box 206)
      - Young Lawyer Division: Prison Committee (Box 206)
      - Civil rights cases: 1988 term (Box 206)
      - Aliens and guns (Box 206)
      - False arrest (Box 206)
      - Drug raid, discrimination (Box 206)
      - Spanish speaking inmates not able to receive correspondence in Spanish (Box 206)
      - Riverside High: student press and censorship (Box 206)
      - Charlotte Housing Authority: curfew (Box 206)
      - Pulled over without cause (Box 206)
      - Sexual discrimination (Box 206)
      - Buncombe County, religious discrimination (Box 206)
      - Defamation, slander (Box 206)
      - Police brutality (Box 206)
      - Harassment by Harnett County police (Box 206)
      - Search without warrant (Box 206)
      - Police misconduct (Box 206)
      - Held without probable cause, 1 of 2 folders (Box 206)
      - Held without probable cause, 2 of 2 folders (Box 207)
      - Ineffective assistance of counsel (Box 207)
      - Prisoner visitation issue (Box 207)
      - Graduate student with visual impairment not given proper assistance in administration of an exam (Box 207)
      - Guilford Technical Community College free speech (Box 207)
      - High Point: downtown pan handling ban (Box 207)
      - Property forfeiture (Box 207)
      - School search (Box 207)
      - Libel (Box 207)
      - Illegal search (Box 207)
      - Loan denial, racial discrimination (Box 207)
      - Police misconduct (Box 207)
      - Haywood County personnel policy (Box 207)
      - Pender County: voting rights (Box 207)
      - Excessive force (Box 207)
      - Prisoner rights (Box 208)
      - Goldsboro library, children's book about a gay librarian (Box 208)
      - Employment discrimination (Box 208)
      - Renewal Center of the South: discrimination against recovering Alcoholics (Box 208)
      - Currituck County: religion and public school (Box 208)
      - Rape not investigated (Box 208)
      - Defamation (Box 208)
      - Rejects, 1993 Mar. (Box 208)
      - Police brutality (Box 208)
      - Police brutality (Box 208)
      - Police brutality (Box 208)
      - Rejects, 1992 July-1993 Jan. (Box 208)
      - Raleigh flag ban (Box 208)
      - Police brutality (Box 208)
      - HIV discrimination (Box 208)
      - Police brutality (Box 208)
      - Not enough signatures to get on the ballot (Box 208)
      - Food Lion: The Independent wrote an article about Food Lion's treatment of employees, and Food Lion stopped carrying The Independent (Box 208)
      - Nash County Board of Elections, religious voter oaths (Box 208)
      - Prisoner rights (Box 208)
      - Termination of lease, due process (Box 208)
      - Social Security Act and illegitimate children (Box 209)
      - Religious discrimination (Box 209)
      - Lumberton riot (Box 209)
      - Students' rights (Box 209)
      - Excessive force (Box 209)
      - White driver pulled over in a black neighborhood (Box 209)
      - Search without reasonable suspicion (Box 209)
      - Computer error results in erroneous arrest (Box 209)
      - Boy wants to play on all-girls volleyball team (Box 209)
      - Erroneous taxation (Box 209)
      - Police misconduct (Box 209)
      - Harassment by law enforcement (Box 209)
      - Teacher jerked a student's arm (Box 209)
      - 4th Amendment (Box 209)
      - NCCLU Prisoners' Rights Project, UNC (Box 209)
      - Due process, judge assisted prosecution (Box 209)
      - Due process, 2 folders (Box 209)
      - Young Lawyers Division, Prison Issues Committee, 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 210)
      - Prisoner rights (Box 210)
      - Attorney's fees/financial structures (Box 210)
      - Indonesian Visitors (Box 210)
      - Knock and announce rule (Box 210)
      - Death Penalty applied to minors (Box 210)
      - Richmond County Radioactive Waste, 2 folders (Box 210)
      - Humanist Counselor (Box 210)
      - Death penalty (Box 210)
      - Racial discrimination (Box 211)
      - Garner Police, use of force (Box 211)
      - High Point and topless bars (Box 211)
      - Due process (Box 211)
      - First Amendment (Box 211-223)
        A First Amendment case involving the censorship of a painting, Sex, Laws, and Coathangers, barred from lobby display in federal building in Raleigh due to its graphic content.
      - Art slides, possibly research for First Amendment case, 2 folders (Box 223)
      - Chatham County v. NC Low-Level Radioactive Waste Authority: due process in finding suitable disposal site according to Authority guidelines, 3 folders (Box 223)
      - Albermarle personnel ordinance (Box 224)
      - HIV discrimination at state mental hospital (Box 224)
      - Employee drug testing (Box 224)
      - First amendment case: rulings (Box 224)
      - Negligence and false imprisonment (Box 224)
      - Cable access channel, policy barring images of non-incumbent political candidates (Box 224)
      - Property seizure upon arrest (Box 224)
      - Off-work conduct (Box 224)
      - Jaycees running whites-only little league (Box 224)
      - Haywood County suppression of high school play Bats in the Belfry (Box 224)
      - Search of garbage without warrant (Box 224)
      - Deceptive trade practices (Box 224)
      - Marine discharged, accused of being a lesbian (Box 224)
      - Retaliatory threats of withholding business for published letter critical of Dare County Commission (Box 224)
      - Randolph Community College: prayer meeting (Box 224)
      - Highway patrol misconduct (Box 224)
      - Due process (Box 224)
      - Ku Klux Klan v. Statesville: parade permit suit (Box 224)
      - Laotian refugees: taken advantage of by McCrae Industries, subdivision, high interest rates (Box 224)
      - Just cause in discharge of an employee (Box 224)
      - Stanley Rescue Squad: First Amendment issue (Box 224)
      - NC controlled substance act (Box 224)
      - Jacksonville anti-loitering ordinance (Box 224)
      - DA's control of criminal calender (Box 224)
      - Rejected case files, 1 of 3 folders (Box 224)
      - Rejected case files, 2 and 3 of 3 folders (Box 225)
      - Gay rights, death of life-partner, denied spousal status (Box 225)
      - Unauthorized distribution of prisoner's HIV status (Box 225)
      - City employee ordinance barring political candidacy (Box 225)
      - Termination from employment in Brunswick County for religion and race (Box 225)
      - Randolph Community College prayer meeting (Box 225)
      - Asheville police officers: termination of employee benefits (Box 225)
      - Illegal entry and search, Atlantic Beach (Box 225)
      - Dismissal from volunteer fire rescue squad for speaking at a public meeting, Gaston County (Box 225)
      - Student roster does not reflect mixed race background (Box 225)
      - Discriminatory custody order against mother's bisexuality (Box 225)
      - Gay/Lesbian rights (Box 225)
      - Schools (Box 225)
      - Central prison executions (Box 225)
      - Necessaries clause (Box 225)
      - Child needs medical procedure, parents object, state assuming custody on claim of neglect, 1 of 5 folders (Box 225)
      - Child needs medical procedure, parents object, state assuming custody on claim of neglect, 2-5 of 5 folders (Box 226)
      - Unlawful detention, 4 folders (Box 226)
      - Carolina Beach, adult entertainment facilities (Box 226)
      - Department of corrections (Box 226)
      - Cable access show about strippers moved to a midnight time-slot by order of the City of Raleigh, forcing breach of previous contract (Box 226)
      - Drug forfeiture laws (Box 226)
      - Durham, The Opportunity Place: establishment clause (Box 226)
      - Free-speech, board enforcing protacted and subjective review of an unofficial student published literary magazine, 7 folders (Box 226)
      - Reprimanded for attending Albermarle city council meeting, 2 folders (Box 226)
      - Inmates with HIV (Box 226)
      - Massage parlor ordinance (Box 226)
      - Prayer at school, Lumberton (Box 226)
      - Greensboro Recreation Dept.: closing of college park basketball courts, 2 folders (Box 226)
      - Art censorship, 3 folders (Box 226)
      - Religious attire in prison (Box 227)
      - Freedom of expression (Box 227)
      - Loss of custody without counsel (Box 227)
      - Religious discrimination against Muslim inmates (Box 227)
      - Retaliation of employer for exercise of First Amendment Rights (Box 227)
      - Ku Klux Klan: Statesville parade permit (Box 227)
      - Search of garbage previous to obtaining a warrant, 5 folders (Box 227)
      - Laotian people, Montgomery County (Box 227)
      - Malicious intent (Box 227)
      - City of Lowell: donations to Salvation Army, violation of establishment clause (Box 227)
      - Macon County Board of Education: restriction of student to health care information (Box 227)
      - Marine discharged, accused of being a lesbian (Box 227)
      - Threats and intimidation by Dare County officials in response to letter to the editor (Box 227)
      - Mitchell County YMCA: County donations to YMCA, violation of establishment clause (Box 227)
      - Prisoner's mail (Box 227)
      - HIV status, privacy issue (Box 227)
      - Muslims, religious discrimination in jails (Box 227)
      - DATA discount fare policy (Box 227)
      - Arrest without probable cause, Rowan County (Box 227)
      - Realty credit policy (Box 227)
      - Foster care (Box 227)
      - Disclosure of HIV status (Box 227)
      - Raleigh Housing Authority: Habitat for Humanity (Box 227)
      - Religious discrimination against Muslim inmates (Box 227)
      - Student refusal to sell candy (Box 227)
      - ROTC: gender discrimination (Box 227)
      - Inmates forced to build furniture for private use of prison's employees (Box 228)
      - Statute against distribution of anonymous campaign literature, 5 folders (Box 228)
      - DA's power over criminal courts (Box 228)
      - Graham County football coach dismissed from employment for lack of religion (Box 228)
      - State delegation of police force to private institutions, 5 folders (Box 228)
      - Death penalty (Box 228)
      - Rescheduling of cable access show, 2 folders (Box 228)
      - Parental consent, 1-13 of 24 folders (Box 229)
      - Parental consent, 14-24 of 24 folders (Box 230)
    - 2000s Case Files, 1998-2005
      Files appear to be mostly generated by Seth Jaffee, chief attorney on staff. Some material ranges from 1990s-2000s and include files generated by Deborah Ross. As with other legal files, the names of the defendants and others have been redacted from this collection guide but are present on folder titles in the boxes.
      - Greens of Pine Glen (Box 231)
      - Henderson Co. Sheriff's Department/Religious display (Box 231)
      - Hope Pregnancy Crisis Center (Box 231)
      - Iredell, Statesville schools: Bible District (Box 231)
      - Lakeside School: morning prayer (Box 231)
      - Murphy Middle School (Box 231)
      - Orange High School: gay/straight alliance (Box 231)
      - Pasquotank County High School: prom (Box 231)
      - Person County School Dress Code (Box 231)
      - Radical Queers, Raleigh Protest (Box 231)
      - Richmond Community College (Box 231)
      - Raleigh police brutality case (Box 231)
      - State of NC v. Nathaniel L. Simpson (Box 231)
      - Town of Clayton: sectarian prayers opening government board meetings (Box 231)
      - Town of Oak Island: political sign (Box 231)
      - Town of Summerfield: public comments rules (Box 231)
      - Yadkinville Ord: adult care homes (Box 231)